Chas Nelson

PhD. MSci

Current Position

2019-current Lord Kelvin Adam Smith Data Science Research Fellow, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK. The opportunity to establish an independent research career focussing on the development of smart microscopy tools and data analysis pipelines for exploring the development of neural computations.

Employment

2018–2019 EPSRC Doctoral Prize Research Fellow, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.

Simulating the optics and light response of the zebrafish retina to evaluate the possiblity of combining light sheet microscopy and graph theoretics to interrogate zebrafish retinal development.

2017-2018

Research Assistant in Microscopy and Optics, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.

Combining real-time image processing with low phototoxicity microscopy to capture synchronised 3D images of the in vivo, beating zebrafish heart.

Education

2013–2017 **PhD in Computer Science**, *Durham University*, Durham, UK.

Thesis: Mathematical Morphology for Quantification in Biological & Medical Image Analysis

2009-2013 Master of Science, Durham University, Durham, UK, First Class Honours.

Biology & Physics within the Natural Sciences Programme

PhD Thesis

Title Mathematical Morphology for Quantification in Biological & Medical Image Analysis

Supervisor Dr Boguslaw Obara

- Description o Developing, validating & disseminating image analysis & processing solutions
 - Vessel enhancement based on morphological operations
 - o Automated and accurate nuclei detection in fluorescent micrographs
 - o Brain vasculature segmentation and aneurysm highlighting in MRA images

Masters Thesis

Title The Scratch Wound Assay: Scratching Away at Cancer with Image Analysis

Supervisor Prof. Chris Hutchison

Description o Developed a scratch wound assay analysis solution capable of tracking individual cells & of analysing wound area

Experiences

Research-related

2020-current Consultant Data Scientist, Fjelltopp, UK.

- o Supported Fjelltop in delivering WHO public health projects
- o Helped analysis and visualise data for a WHO project on emergency services in Ukraine. Focussed on developing a series of interactive maps supporting the exploration of data themes at a regional level

- 2018–2019 Undergraduate Supervisor, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Designed and supervised the undergraduate research projects of three students
 - o Guided students through theory, experimental design, programming, research and reporting
 - o Provided pastoral support for getting summer interships and applying for further study and jobs
- 2018–2019 Vacation Scholarship Supervisor, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Awarded EPSRC and local funding for four undergraduate students to complete research projects
 - o Designed coherent research programmes for the students and supervised them throughout the project
 - o Guided students through complex theory, experimental design, data analysis and presenting skills
 - 2017 Conference Organiser, Glasgow Imaging Network, University Glasgow, UK.
 - o Organised a one-day conference to bring together life scientists, physicists and engineers working on the development or use of imaging technologies
 - \circ The conference was a great success with 23 % of attendees establishing new collaborations
- 2016–2017 **Founding Director**, Intogral Ltd., UK.
 - o Helped set-up a new company focussed on innovative and intelligent image analysis solutions
 - o Developed a Innovate UK bids for early funding
 - o Dealt with legal and financial aspects of setting up and running a small start up
- 2016-2017 Undergraduate Supervisor, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham, UK.
 - o Designed and supervised the undergraduate research projects of three students
 - o The report of one of Frank Ryan was highly commened in the 2016 Undergraduate Awards
 - o Guided students through theory, experimental design, programming, research and reporting
 - o Provided pastoral support for getting summer interships and applying for further study and jobs
- 2015–2017 Founder Journal Club, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham University, UK.
 - o Founded the Vision Journal Club to help postgraduates develop their critical analysis skills
 - o The club focuses on image processing, computer vision & visualisation papers
 - o Chaired the club, organising papers & leading discussions
- 2015–2017 Junior Seminars Chair, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham University, UK.
 - o Chaired the Computer Science Junior Seminar series of lectures
 - o Invited speakers & organised sessions across a range of areas of interest

Teaching

- 2019 Bioimage analysis with Python, (IAFIG) Royal Microscopical Society, London, UK.
 - o Part of the organising and teaching team for a week long course on bioimage analysis
 - o Taught on the basics of image processing, manipulating images with Python and integrating Python and FIJI into one pipeline
- 2019 Programming for Biologists, Royal Society of Biology, London, UK.
 - o Developed a one day, intensive, zero-to-hero Python course for biologists
 - o Including in-course and after-course teaching materials and on-line support videos
- 2018–2019 Python Computing Course, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Developed a new Python programming course for the level 2 Physics undergraduate module
 - $\,\circ\,$ Designed new teaching materials within the Jupyter Notebooks framework
- 2017–2018 Polarisation Practical Lab Design, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Developed a new lab for the level 2 physics undergraduate module
 - o Whilst the practical focused on experimenting with polarisation it was developed with the development of key skills as a focus
- 2017–2019 Frontiers in Physics Lectures, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - $\circ\,$ Lectured on Imaging the Developing Zebrafish Heart as part of level 1 undergraduate physics course.
- 2016–2017 Bioimage Analysis Lectures, School of Biological & Biomedical Sciences, Durham University,
 - o Lectured on Bioimage Analysis as part of level 3/4 undergraduate course Biological Imaging
 - o Developed digital imaging & image analysis curriculum & content for multidisciplinary cohort
- 2015–2017 **Postgraduate CPD Series**, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham University, UK.
 - o Developed a curriculum of CPD topics, $\it e.g.$ delivering a conference talk, for the PhD cohort
 - o Delivered a seminar on the wide range of visualisation a plotting tools available to students

Policy

- 2018 Transparency of Evidence, Sense about Science, UK.
 - o A Spot Check of Government Policy Proposals July 2016 to July 2017
 - o The spotcheck scored "94 government policies [on] how transparent [was] the evidence behind the policy."
 - o Contributed as a policy scorer of government policies
- 2018 Member of Policy Sub-Committee, Royal Society of Biology in Scotland, Scotland, UK.
 - o Actively involved in the policy work of the RSB in Scotland
 - o Contributed to and edited collated responses to calls for evidence
 - o Involved in developing a database of routes into life science careers in Scotland
- 2016 Strategy & Policy Intern, BBSRC, Swindon, UK.
 - o Part of the Exploiting New Ways of Working science strategy group
 - o Contributed to the BBSRC UK-wide direction & strategy for bioimaging and related technologies
 - o Produced the public BBSRC Review of Bioimaging report
 - o Developed quantitative & qualitative data analysis along with exciting visualisations
 - o Delivered findings at high-profile meetings, e.g. with members of BIS, the UK governmental department in charge of science research funding
- 2012 MURN Researcher, Matariki Undergraduate Research Network, Durham, UK.
 - o Established a global research plan into interdisciplinary science in teaching & research
 - o Produced an internal report for Durham University that has since been used for internal strategy
 - o Collaborated with a global team including researchers from Australia and New Zealand
 - o Undertook training in qualitative research & education research

Outreach

- 2019 Presenter, Explorathon 2019, Glasgow, UK, Seeing the Invisible.
- 2019 **Presenter**, Glasgow Science Festival Science Sunday, Glasgow, UK, Using the Rainbow-Imaging with Colours of Light.
- 2019 Speaker, Pint of Science, Glasgow, UK, Imaging the Zebrafish Heart Without Breaking It.
- 2019 **Speaker**, 7 Minutes of Science, Glasgow, UK, Imaging the Beating Zebrafish Heart.
- 2019 Speaker, Café Scientifique Cockermouth, Cockermouth, UK, Revolutions in Light Microscopy.
- 2019 Speaker, University of the Third Age, Glasgow, UK, Revolutions in Modern Light Microscopy.
- 2018 Speaker, Café Scientifique Glasgow, Glasgow, UK, Revolutions in Light Microscopy.
- 2018 Speaker, Institute of Physics Scotland Public Lecture Series, Glasgow, UK, Imaging the Developing Heart: Combining Computing and Optics to Image and Quantify a Highly Dynamic System.
- 2013 Co-Founder, Durham City Café Scientifique, Durham, UK.

Other Experiences and Responsibilities

2017-current Mental Health Awareness Events, College of Science & Engineering, University of Glasgow, UK.

- o Organised college-wide Stress and Resilience panel evnet for University Mental Health Day 2020
- o Organised school-wide events for Time to Talk Day 2020 including a poster campaigna and coffee morning
- o Organised school-wide events for Mental Health Awareness Week 2019 including a poster campaign, coffee morning, Glasgow Women in Physics-joint event and a picnic
- o Organised school-wide events for World Mental Health Day 2018 including a coffee morning and mental health colloquium
- o Organised college-wide events for Mental Health Awareness Week 2018 including a poster campaign, coffee morning and a panel discussion from Mental Health First Aiders

2017–current Council Member, Royal Society for Biology in Scotland, Scotland, UK.

- o Elected Ordinary Member of the RSB in Scotland Council (charity no. 277981)
- o Part of the Policy Committee
- o Involved in a variety of Scotland and UK-wide policy and outreach activities

2015–2017 Trustee, Ustinov College Graduate Common Room, Durham, UK.

- o Trustee of a registered charitable body (no. 1164865)
- o Part of Durham's historic listed collegiate system
- o Ensured charity carried out its purpose for the benefit of the college members
- o Complied with charity law and The Charity Commission
- o Ensured accountability of the charity and its executive board

Awards, Grants & Honours

2019-current Lord Kelvin Adam Smith Research Fellowship in Data Science

- Covers full salary and £10,000 research funds per year
- 2019 Royal Microscopical Society Travel Grant (£300)
- 2019 Royal Society of Biology Outreach and Engagement Grant (£500)
- 2018–2019 EPSRC Doctoral Prize Research Fellowship
 - Covers full salary
 - 2018 Glasgow Imaging Network 1st Prize Poster Award (Nikon DSLR Camera)
 - 2018 Institute of Physics Early Career Researchers Fund (£300)
 - 2018 Honor Fell/Company of Biologists Travel Award (£500)
 - 2018 EPSRC Vacation Scholarship (£2,300)
 - Awarded funds to support an undergraduate student during a ten week summer project
 - 2016 Wolfson Research Institute Small Grants Award (£2,000)
 - 2015 1st prize Images of Technology @ Durham 2015
- 2014–2017 Biophysical Sciences Institute Junior Fellowship
 - Awarded to researchers with significant experience in interdisciplinary life science research
 - 2013 EPSRC PhD Studentship (3.5 years; £19,126 per annum)
 - 2013 Institute for Advanced Computing Research Grant (£2,000)
 - 2013 Honor Fell/Company of Biologists Travel Award Full registration and accommodation costs at the BSCB-BSDB Joint Spring Meeting 2013
 - 2012 Matariki Undergraduate Research Network Research Grant (£2,000)

Publications

Professional Bodies

2018-current Member of the Sense about Science Voice of Young Science Network

2016-current Member of the Royal Society of Biology, MRSB

• Elected Ordinary Member of the RSB in Scotland Council

2016-current Member of the Royal Microscopical Society, MRMS

2016-current Associate Fellow of the Higher Education Academy

Online Presence

• https://www.chasnelson.co.uk

Blog The Little Eye: chasnelson.co.uk/thelittleeye @ChasNelson1990

ChasNelson1990

ORCID 0000-0002-4114-1710